<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Luke Holman on Luke Holman</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Luke Holman on Luke Holman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 16:04:59 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary simulations of Z-linked suppression gene drives</title>
      <link>/publication/w_shredder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 16:04:59 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/w_shredder/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Researchers collaborate with same-gendered colleagues more often than expected across the life sciences</title>
      <link>/publication/homophily/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 15:49:03 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/homophily/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative transcriptomics of social insect queen pheromones</title>
      <link>/publication/pheromone_rnaseq/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 16:04:59 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/pheromone_rnaseq/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sexual selection improves population fitness: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
      <link>/publication/justin_metaanalysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 16:04:59 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/justin_metaanalysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Queen pheromones</title>
      <link>/project/queen_pheromones/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 16:40:37 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/queen_pheromones/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Queen pheromones are chemical signals produced by reproductive females, or queens, in social insects such as bees, ants, wasps, and termites. I am especially interested in queen pheromones that cause other colony members to become sterile, because reproductive division of labour is the defining &amp;ndash; and most evolutionarily striking &amp;ndash; characteristic of the social insects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been working on queen pheromones since 2008, when I conducted the first experimental bioassay to identify a queen pheromone from an ant (the black garden ant, &lt;em&gt;Lasius niger&lt;/em&gt;). In a series of follow-up papers, we showed that the queen pheromone signals the fecundity and condition and of the queen, suggesting that it is an &amp;lsquo;honest signal&amp;rsquo; of the queen&amp;rsquo;s value to the workers. That is, the workers probably &amp;lsquo;choose&amp;rsquo; to remain sterile when they perceive the presence of a healthy queen, since it is more profitable for them to reproduce indirectly by helping to raise the queen&amp;rsquo;s young (who are usually the workers&amp;rsquo; brothers and sisters).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on, I co-discovered the first queen pheromone for a bumblebee and a wasp, in collaboration with Tom Wenseleers and colleagues. The queen pheromones of most ants, wasps and bees are quite similar, which is surprising given that these three groups evolved their eusocial societies independently, and have been evolving independently for well over 100 million years. This suggests that queen pheromones evolved from some sort of chemical signal (such as a sex pheromone signaling egg production) that was already present in the solitary insects that were the common ancestors of the eusocial Hymenoptera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most recent work focuses on the transcriptomic effects of queen pheromones. As one might expect of a pheromone that profoundly alters the behaviour and physiology of workers exposed to it, we find that queen pheromones affect the expression of a great many genes. We found striking similarity in the genetic circuits targetted by queen pheromones in bees and ants, which are separated by 150 million years of independent evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science about science</title>
      <link>/project/science_about_science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 13:09:44 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/science_about_science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have written on &amp;lsquo;p-hacking&amp;rsquo;, the phenomenon wherby people fudge the numbers in various ways in order to get the coveted p &amp;lt; 0.05. Our work suggests that p-hacking is widespread: there are suspicious bulges in the distribution of published p-values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also written about blind methods, i.e. where the experimenter (and the subjects, if they are people) cannot identify the treatment groups, and thus consciously or unconsciously add bias. Our work found that blind methods are used less often than they should be, and that it really matters: non-blind studies tend to yield results that fall in the predicted direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recently, I have been working on the &amp;lsquo;gender gap&amp;rsquo; in science. See the gender gap project for more inforation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sexual selection</title>
      <link>/project/sexual_selection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 19:20:48 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sexual_selection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m especially interested in understanding how sexual selection affects population mean fitness; it can bring benefits by helping to declutter the genome of mutations, yet the resulting inter- and intra-genomic conflicts that come with sexual selection can be considerable. I work on sexual selection using a combination of experiments with insects, theoretical models, quantitative genetics, and transcriptomics. I have also written about honest signalling, and during my PhD I worked mostly on the evolution of &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; sperm morphology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gene drives</title>
      <link>/project/gene_drives/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 19:00:21 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/gene_drives/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Gene drives&amp;rdquo; are alleles that spread through populations due to within-individual selection, instead of by increasing the fitness of individuals that carry them. For example, the genetic elements &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Segregation distorter&lt;/em&gt; occur naturally in mice and fruitflies respectively; they are able to spread through populations despite reducing the fitness of indiviuals that carry them because they &amp;ldquo;selfishly&amp;rdquo; ensure their own transmission to ~95% of the offspring of male heterozygotes. Gene drives can work in a variety of ways, including destroying sperm cells that do not carry them, biasing meiosis in females, or gene conversion (which essentially converts drive heterozygotes into homozygotes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, it has become possible to artificially create gene drives using genome editing technologies such as CRISPR-Cas9. These artificial drives could be used in the near future to genetically engineer or eradicate populations of wild organisms (e.g. to prevent the spread of malaria). However, gene drive research still has many hurdles &amp;ndash; technological, regulatory, and ethical &amp;ndash; to overcome. Aside from the challenging lab work needed to build a functional gene drive, many issues remain unresolved. Will populations evolve resistance to gene drives, or will they spread indefinitely? Can we make truly safe and self-limiting genes, which will remain restricted to the release site or go extinct once their job is done? What is the optimal design for a gene drive for each of the applications that they could help with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been fascinated by gene drives ever since I first read about them in &lt;em&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;/em&gt; as a teenager. I intermittently write models and reviews about them, and I am currently working on the naturally-occurring gene drive &lt;em&gt;Segregation distorter&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intralocus sexual conflict</title>
      <link>/project/intralocus_conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 17:38:27 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/intralocus_conflict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Intralocus sexual conflict occurs when different trait values are favoured by selection on males versus females, but each sex is constrained from evolving towards its own phenotypic optimum by genetic correlations between male and female traits. For example, the selectively optimum body size is often different between the sexes, yet male and female body size are largely affected by the same loci, meaning that the sexes evolve to some sort of maladaptive compromise (creating the so-called &amp;lsquo;gender load&amp;rsquo;). Intralocus sexual conflict is a fascinating process with many improlications for conservation biology, as well as many of the big questions in evolutionary biology (such as the evolution of sex problem and the lek paradox).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution in social insects</title>
      <link>/project/social_insects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 16:10:20 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/social_insects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The eusocial insects (e.g. bees, ants, wasps, and termites) are united by a remakable trait: some individuals give up the opportunity to reproduce, and instead acts as helpers to enhance the reproduction of other individuals. I am interested in how and why the social insect &amp;lsquo;caste system&amp;rsquo; of queens and workers evolved, and how evolution has shaped their biology. I am especially interested in the role of queen pheromones in evolution and colony life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The gender gap in science: how long until women are equally represented?</title>
      <link>/publication/gender_gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 13:06:30 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/gender_gap/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of female choice under intralocus sexual conflict and genotype-by-environment interactions</title>
      <link>/publication/li_and_holman/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 13:06:30 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/li_and_holman/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Onwards and upwards: a response to comments on Holman</title>
      <link>/publication/be_reply/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 16:26:57 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/be_reply/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Queen pheromones and reproductive division of labor: a meta-analysis</title>
      <link>/publication/qp_meta_analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 17:56:34 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/qp_meta_analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The gender gap in science</title>
      <link>/project/gender_gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 14:03:47 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/gender_gap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the 2018 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/metrics?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.2004956#viewedHeader&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PLoS Biology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; paper, we found that there is a striking shortage of women in many fields of science and medicine. Inspired by earlier studies that manually counted the number of men and women publishing in scientific journals, we developed computational approaches to infer the gender of 36 million authors publishing articles indexed on PubMed and ar$\chi$iv over recent decades. By applying statistical models, we projected when the gender gap will close for dozens of fields of research. The results were bleak: many fields will take decades or centuries to reach gender parity, assuming that the current (slow) rate of progress continues. I have a couple more projects in the works on the massive dataset generated by the project, and I need some help! Drop me a line if you&amp;rsquo;d like to discuss a collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made an &lt;a href=&#34;https://lukeholman.github.io/genderGap/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;interactive web app&lt;/a&gt; to help you fully explore the data. All the data (e.g. the gender ratio breakdown for thousands of journals, disciplines, and countries; data on the 36m individual papers) is freely available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lukeholman/genderGapCode&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;d be very happy if it proves useful to someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/metrics?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.2004956#viewedHeader&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PLoS Biology&lt;/a&gt; paper was widely covered in the media, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2018/04/when-will-the-gender-gap-in-science-disappear/558413/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ed Yong&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/new-study-says-the-gender-gap-in-science-could-take-generations-to-fix-95150&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-43826143&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt;. According to Altmetric it&amp;rsquo;s been seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.altmetric.com/details/38251072/twitter&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;3.7 million times&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also written a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/06/14/345975&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;follow-up paper&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://tuhat.helsinki.fi/portal/en/persons/claire-morandin(05fda6f6-ba4f-42b2-a915-7a0ea26c5088).html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Claire Morandin&lt;/a&gt;, using this dataset to look at patterns of collaboration within and between genders. We found that researchers have strong tendency to collaborate with same-gendered colleagues, in essentially all fields of research. Interestingly, we found a weak negative correlation between journal impact factor and the excess of same-gender coauthorships, as predicted if mixed-gender teams produce better quality research.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
